Ann Eve Moss Papers, 1920-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ann Eve Moss Papers, 1920-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-028
1 cu. ft.
Materials include photographs, playbills, news clippings, and other memorabilia from Moss's early career as a chorus girl for the Ziegfield Follies, as well as manuscript copies of her unpublished novels.
Ann Eve Moss
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Ann Eve Moss papers were donated to Special Collections in July 1990.
Biographical Information
Ann Moss, nee Dressler, was born in New York City in 1903. She took singing and dancing lessons in high school and began performing on the professional stage by the time she graduated. She married Harry Moss, a theatrical agent, in 1922. She spent the years between 1922 and 1930 as a Ziegfeld Follies chorus girl in such productions as The Three Musketeers, Garrick Gaieties, and Funny Face. Moss also modeled for New York Daily News advertisements. In 1927 she gave birth to her only daughter, Marilyn (later known as Alwyn). In 1928 she refused to audition in the nude for producer Earl Carroll's show Fioretta, brought charges against Carroll before Actor's Equity, the theater union, and won the case in January 1929.
In the late 1930s Moss traveled to Europe, the beginning of a series of trips abroad throughout the remainder of her life. Upon her return to the U.S. she launched into her writing career, and completed the first draft of the novel Catha's Sister, based on her experiences on the stage. When her marriage ended in the early 1940s, she became a freelance secretary. Her employers included Erich Fromm, Rollo May, Countess Mona Bismarck (for whom she later worked full time as an administrative secretary on her estate in Capri, Italy), and Paul Pierre Matisse, son of the painter, for whom she worked in Nice, France. During this time she also worked on another novel, A Widow's Odyssey (unpublished). Other, shorter works include children's books The Friends of Tinkle Rescue Club and The Runaway Balloon (unpublished). She moved to Nice in the mid-1960s and returned the United States in 1975, settling in Greensboro, North Carolina. In 1981 she moved to Floyd, Virginia, to live with her daughter, and in 1984 moved to a retirement community in Blacksburg, Virginia. She died five days before her 85th birthday in March 1988.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the materials in the collection consist of photographs, news clippings, correspondence, literary manuscripts, and playbills collected or created by Moss from the 1920s to her death. Copies of her two unpublished novels, Catha's Sister and A Mystic Smile, are included here, as well as several of her other shorter writings. The news clippings include editorials from New York papers regarding Moss's lawsuit against Earl Carroll. The photographs include many where she appears as a character from the various plays in which she performed, as well as several portrait poses. Other materials include correspondence, news clippings, and programs from meetings of The Ziegfeld Club, an organization of former Ziegfeld Follies chorus girls. A draft of the introduction to The Friends of Tinkle Rescue Club, written by Alwyn Moss, is also included.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Family photographs, 1900-1940. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Newspaper clippings, 1920-1929. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Playbills, 1920-1929. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Photographs (stagework and posed), 1920-1929. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Correspondence, 1920-1939. (Box-folder 1:5)
- The Runaway Balloon, 1940s. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Catha's Sister, (Copy 1); Chapters 1-15, 1940s. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Catha's Sister, (Copy 1); Chapters 16-35, 1940s. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Catha's Sister, (Copy 2); Chapters 1-15, 1940s. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Catha's Sister, (Copy 2); Chapters 16-35, 1940s. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Passports, 1954-1959. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Correspondence, 1957-1986. (Box-folder 1:12)
- A Widow's Odyssey, Chapters 1-7, 1960s. (Box-folder 2:1)
- A Widow's Odyssey, Chapters 8-17, 1960s. (Box-folder 2:2)
- A Widow's Odyssey, Chapters 18-27, 1960s. (Box-folder 2:3)
- The Ten Minute Elixir, 1975-1981. (Box-folder 2:4)
- Feasts without Flesh, 1975-1981. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Newspaper clippings, 1975-1985. (Box-folder 2:6)
- Ziegfield Club meeting programs, 1976-1982. (Box-folder 2:7)
- Friends of Tinkle Rescue Club, circa 1983. (Box-folder 2:8)
- A Year in Paris, 1984. (Box-folder 2:9)
- Elderhostel certificates, 1984-1986. (Box-folder 2:10)
- Correspondence and Lists (literary agents and publishers), 1985. (Box-folder 2:11)
- Miscellaneous, regarding The Widow's Odyssey and Catha's Sister, 1985-1986. (Box-folder 2:12)
- The Lamp on the Roof, 1986. (Box-folder 3:1)
- The View of the Hour magazine contest, 1986. (Box-folder 3:2)
- Information regarding Moss's death, 1988. (Box-folder 3:3)
- Article about Moss from the Roanoke Times and World News and The Shining Spirit of a Star by Tracy Wimmer, 1985-1986. (Box-folder 3:4)
- Introduction to Friends of Tinkle Rescue Club by Alwyn Moss, 1990. (Box-folder 3:5)
- Outline for an unnamed play, undated. (Box-folder 3:6)
- A Trader's Paradise, undated. (Box-folder 3:7)
- Miscellaneous notes and papers, undated. (Box-folder 3:8)
- Photographs and newspaper clippings, 1928, 1920s. (Box-folder Oversize)